[music]
Doesn't this look like something's going
to drop from the ceiling? Like a ground
zero type thing? [snorts]
Be honest. It's like who has the buzzer
that if I'm I really suck, they press it
and everything falls down through the
trap door. No.
>> Be careful.
>> Yeah. Okay. Who was it?
>> Okay. You tell me if I'm doing okay or
if I should take a couple of steps back.
Right. So, hi everyone. I'm Assaf. Um,
and I'm here to talk about Genbi. And
kind of first disclaimer, this
presentation was not created with Gen
AI. Um to be honest, I actually started
doing it uh with uh GPT03 back in
August. [snorts] Uh and then I did kind
of a first draft and then a couple of
weeks back I wanted to come in and
refresh it before the conference and
then GPT5 took over completely messed up
my slides. So I ended up doing it
manually kind of old-fashioned. So if
I'm missing like an M dash somewhere in
the middle, let me know after. Okay.
[snorts]
Uh so first of all, a bit of
housekeeping. What's GenBBI? So, it's a
fusion of Gen AI and BI. It's basically
an agent that helps people answer
business questions with data like a a
business intelligence person would do in
real life. [snorts] Uh, the reason that
we're pursuing GenBI is really because
of the data democratization that it can
bring, right? So having access to data
at your fingertips without having to be
reliant on a BI team that helps you find
a report, figure out what it means, uh,
understand your world before they can
even give you any kind of input. Uh, so
that's GenBBI. Uh, a bit about
Northwestern Mutual. That's where I
work. So we're a financial services,
life insurance, and wealth management.
Been around for 160 years. [snorts] Uh,
some very impressive numbers there. But
first of all, I want to say why is
Northwestern Mutual a great place to do
Gen AI. We got a lot of data, we got a
lot of money, we got a lot of use cases,
and we got access to some of the best
talent uh anyone can dream of. Really
truly humbled by the people that I get
to work with. Um but on the flip side,
why is it hard to do Gen AI at
Northwestern Mutual? Because it is a
very riskaverse company, right? If you
think about it, our main motto is
generational responsibility. I call it
don't f up. Uh because what we end
up selling to people is a decadesl long
commitment, right? You buy life
insurance now. Uh if you stay with us
until it comes to term, so to speak,
that can be 20, 40, 80 years down the
line, depending on when you buy it and
how long you get to live. And so
stability is something that's very
important for us because it's important
for our clients. So how do we balance
stability with innovation? That's what I
want to talk about today. Um and really
the four main challenges that we had
when we even came up with the idea kind
of a pie in the sky Genbi concept. Uh
[snorts] first of all, no one's done it
before, right? Truly, no one's done
Genbi in this fashion in the past. Uh
secondly, and this was really a
preference for us. We wanted to use
actual data that's messy because we knew
that those were that's where the real
challenges are going to be, right?
Understanding actual messy data for 160y
old company and how can we perform well
within that ecosystem. Um the third was
kind of a blind trust bias. So um the bi
the trust that we had to build was both
with the users but also with the
leadership of the company right how can
we bring accurate information accurate
answers to people when uh all of these
things that we know about and everyone's
talked about is is just out there right
no one's blind to the trust barriers no
one's blind to the accuracy barriers so
how do we convince that this is actually
something that we can trust in the
company and lastly
Um but really firstly when we go to
approach this from an enterprise
perspective [snorts] budget the impact
right how do we convince someone in a
leadership uh organization where risk
aversement is ingrained in the DNA to
even invest in something like this that
no one's done before we don't really
know how we would do it uh we're not
even sure how it would look like when it
comes to turn
uh so I'll start kind of one by one uh
and first of all really talk about why
we chose to use actual data uh and not
synthesized data or cleanse data.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh so really it's about making sure that
we understand the actual complexities
that we will have to face when we
eventually want to go to production
right we know that you know building uh
PC's and demos is so easy but the gap
from PC to production is so broad uh
especially in this gen AI space
especially because we don't know upfront
how to design the system what we would
expect it to behave like so making sure
that we operate with real data just gave
us that extra confidence that when
something works in the lab it's very
likely to also work in reality. Uh but
also and maybe not uh in the least less
important is that we got to work with
actual people who work with the data day
in and day out and that gave us two
things. Okay, first of all subject
matter expertise which are super
critical for us to be able to validate
that the system is actually working gave
us a lot of real life examples of what
people are actually asking in a
corporate and what people have answered
to them. So basically the eval right and
all the testing and stuff. Uh but at the
end of the day it also brought the
business to be a part of the research
project itself and they became kind of
bought into the idea as part of the
process. So we didn't just test
something in the lab and then had to
convince someone to go ahead and use it.
The end users were part of the research
process itself. And so when eventually
it matured enough so we can take some of
that to production, they were already
there and they actually were pulling
that. They told us we want to take this,
how can we wrap it, how can we package
it uh quickly enough so we can put it
into practice.
Uh and the next part was really about
building trust. Uh so this is about
building trust first of all with our
management team. All right. Now, I don't
know about you, but last time that I got
a million dollar to do a research
project that I wanted in a pie sky idea.
I woke up from the dream and I realized
that this is not how things work in
reality. You don't just get a million
dollars and go ahead and try something
out. Uh, you had to show that you know
what you're doing. And part of what we
did, it's kind of listed out here, but
obviously, you know, we did all the
regular stuff, right? We worked in a
sandbox environment. We made sure that
we're not using actual client data. We
made sure to put in all the security
risk aside. But uh one of the first
approaches that we said we're going to
take is we're not just going to build a
tool that's going to be uh released to
everyone, right? We understood very
quickly that um how people interact with
the tool, their ability to verify that
what they're getting is right and also
give us feedback changes dramatically
depending on their expertise and
understanding of the data. So we took
that crawl, walk, run approach that
basically said we're first going to
release it to actual BI experts, right?
people that would be able to do it on
their own and know what good looks like
when they get it. And we're just going
to expedite the process for them kind of
like a GitHub co-pilot. The next phase
would be to bring it to business
managers and again people who are closer
to the BI team, but when they see a
mistake, they can pretty much figure out
that what they're seeing is wrong
because they're used to seeing that on
day-to-day basis. um and they will might
be less sensitive to these types of
mistakes and be more inclined to give us
that feedback instead of just, you know,
dumping it aside and never using it
again. Giving this type of tool to
executives in the company, I don't even
know when we're going to get there,
right? Like an executive, they want
clear, concise answers that they know
they can trust. We're definitely not
there yet. I think that's the vision uh
at some point in time, but the system is
not accurate enough for us to get there.
Maybe it never will be.
>> [snorts]
>> Um, another way that we another liver
that we kind of used to build inherent
transit the system is that we said,
well, in the get-go, we're not going to
even try to build SQLs, right? This is
very complex. This is very hard even for
a person. So, we said step number one,
let's just bring information that is
already in the ecosystem that's already
verified, right? We have a lot of uh
certified reports and dashboards. Um and
actually in the conversations we had
with some of the BI teams that we worked
with, they told us guys like 80% of the
work that we do is basically sending
people to the right report and helping
them figure out how to use it. So the
report is already there. Um and that
again built some inherent trust into how
we architected the system because we
said we're not going to make up
information. we're just going to deliver
you the same asset that you would have
gotten anyway just in a much faster much
more interactive way. Uh and that was
the alignment of expectations that we
did very upfront with the uh users and
also with the management team.
Now [clears throat]
the biggest um
process or kind of the most important
approach that we took when uh
approaching our leadership team and
convincing them that we want to do this
was to create a very gradual incremental
process that gave them a lot of
visibility and control. Uh and it was
very important for us to build
incremental deliveries throughout that
process so that [snorts] uh not only did
they have the the visibility into what
are we funding now, what do we get out
of it, they actually had business
deliverables they could realize
potential from throughout the process
and at any point in time they could pull
the plug right and say okay like it's
not working well or we got enough out of
it or you know the next phase is so you
know unknown and long that we don't want
further invest in it. And this is how we
basically broke it down. So phase one
was just pure research, right? We kind
of did the shift from natural language
to SQL. We figured out how to write
responses. We figure out how to
understand questions that coming in.
Just kind of setting the stage. [snorts]
Phase two was about really
understanding, okay, so what does good
metadata and good context look like in
the perspective of a BI agent, right? It
looks very different if you're just
chatting with something or if you're
trying to do a rag with you know
unstructured data like documents and uh
business knowledge and stuff like that.
And this phase on its own already had uh
impact on the business because when we
define what good metadata looks like for
an an LLM uh we could immediately apply
that also to just the ecosystem of data
users across the enterprise. Um, and by
understanding how to extract LM from the
information, we could also how to
extract metadata. Sorry, here's where
[snorts] the trap door comes into play,
right? Um, we could also project that on
how or what good metadata looks like for
humans interacting with the data. We
have another initiative around semantic
layer going on which tries to model
exactly that and this provided a very
valuable input to that initiative as
well. But the immediate next step was
basically just doing this kind of uh
multicontext semantic search, right?
People coming in asking different
questions and having the system figure
out what's the right context, what's the
right information we need in uh bring
them. And this is something that could
already be packaged as its own product
and delivered uh and basically just do
kind of a data finder and data owner
finder which is something that could
take anywhere between two to maybe four
weeks in an enterprise like Northwestern
Mutual just finding what data exists and
who owns it so I can start talk uh the
conversation with them.
Um and the next layer was really about
pulling in information and trying to do
some light pivoting around the data. Um
each one of these steps as you can see
also created an input to the to the
following step so that the research
itself was kind of self u
self-propelling and there were
incremental outcomes coming out of each
one of these phases. Uh the next one is
more kind of setting it up for
enterprise level usage. So understanding
roles of in uh of different users coming
in what they may be asking about what
type of access we want to give them etc
and eventually and this is still some
ways to go ahead uh building kind of a
fullyfledged NBI agent which doesn't
only quote information from existing
reports but I can actually run SQL
queries on its own uh pull in more data
do more sophisticated joints between
different data so it can answer more
complex questions so that's the road map
right that's kind the high level plan.
Now, why did that work? Well, kind of
quickly summarize them. We talked about
uh so we get value uh early and we get
value often. Each one of this was a six
week sprint at the end of which we had
had a very tangible deliverable coming
back to the business that we could
decide to productize. Uh and at any
point in time, we could decide how we
want to move forward. There was
transparent progress. There was
incremental business value. Uh each one
of these steps allowed us to learn
something that helped feed the next
step.
And maybe the most important part and
that's the bottom line here and that's
the part that executives really look at.
How do we control the risk in continuing
to invest in this type of research
project and this is really about
eliminating things like sun cost bias,
right? We already paid you know you know
whatever a million dollar. Let's just
get through the project see what we get
at the end. This eliminates the uh uh
fear of of competitors coming in and
maybe we don't need to continue
investing in this right so everyone in
the industry is researching GenBI and
there are solutions like data bricks
genie that are coming up and they're
getting better and better maybe at some
point in time it's better for us as an
organization to actually adopt data
bricks genie but at that point again
first it's much easier for us to pull
the plug and the funding but we already
have a good understanding of what good
looks like we have benchmarks that we
used for ourselves when testing our own
system that we can test a third party
solution with. And we know what to
expect, right? We know what works, we
know what doesn't. We know what a kind
of fluffy demo from a vendor would look
like. And we know where to drill in to
ask the tough questions.
So let's see kind of what it looks like
under the hood and how we productize
different elements uh of this
architecture. Uh and maybe kind of very
quickly, why can't we just do it with uh
chat GPT? So you [snorts] know just
dumping a schema into chachpp doesn't
work. Usually schemas are very messy.
It's not uh easy to understand the
context and the meaning of things.
[snorts] Uh and eventually governance is
super important. So there was a lot of
governance built into the architecture
that was very hard to apply on chpd from
the outside but even solutions like you
know data bricks genius third party much
harder to govern from the outside than
from the inside. But still TBD.
Uh so the stack kind of looks like this.
Uh we have a data and metadata layer
that we produced. We have four different
agents that are running across the
pipeline. A metadata agent that
understands the context. A rag agent
that finds the different reports. An SQL
agent that can pull more data if we need
that. And then eventually what we call a
BI agent that takes all that information
and delivers an answer to the question
that was asked. On top of that, we slap
governance and trust and orchestration
and eventually some kind of a contextual
UI. Um and this is how the flow goes. So
when a business question comes in we uh
push it into the orchestrator and
basically decides how to facilitate the
process. The first thing that we do is
understanding the context. So that's
where that metadata agent comes in works
with the catalog works with all the
documentation that we have across the
system to understand what we're being
asked about and what's the relevant
information to share. Then we go to the
rag agent which tries to find an
existing report again out of a list of
certified reports that we know are
allowed for people to use and people
have spent a lot of time fine-tuning
them and making them as accurate as
possible.
If we can't find the report or if it's
not exactly what we need to um to use,
that's where we go to the SQL agent that
basically tries to create a more um
exact query or a more elaborate query.
And even if the report that we have is
not usable as is, it gives us that
initial seed of a query that we can then
expand on rather than having to build
one from scratch. So it's kind of like a
fewot uh example, but in this case the
example that we give is very very close
to the actual result that we're
expecting to get. We then execute it
against the database pull and push it
into the BI agent which gen with which
gen uh translate that to a business
answer and not just dumping data back on
the user and this is what goes into the
final answer. Now there's obviously some
kind of a loop that says if I'm in the
same conversation I'm probably talking
about the same data so we don't have to
talk about this or do this again and
again. Now
each one of these three components, each
one of these three agents can be
packaged as its own product and
delivered to production with a very
tangible and actual impact on business
metrics. Okay. And that's the kind of
beauty of this uh approach that after we
productize each one of these, we could
have basically said stop or let's move
forward.
uh and just some giving bottom line
numbers around some of these. So just
the rag agent that pulls the right
report uh allowed us to take about 20%
of the overall capacity of the BI team
that basically said uh all we do is just
share the right report with the right
person. So we were able to automate
around 80% out of those uh 20% and we're
talking about a team of 10 people. So
roughly two people full-time job all
they do is find the right report and
send it to the right person.
uh the metadata understandings that we
got from learning how to interact with
the data through an LLM allowed us to
run AB test in a in the semantic layer
project that we did and that allowed us
to prove back again to the senior
leadership in the company that there is
value and tangible value measurable
value in enriching metadata. And we did
that basically by running uh a a battery
of questions um against a database that
had good metadata and one that didn't
have good metadata. And we show how much
better an LLM performs when having the
right metadata in place. So basically
proving the value of something that can
be very fluffy like hey let's bring in
more documentation into the code. Uh
right now we're experimenting with the
data pivoting bot. Uh so once you have a
dashboard or a report be able to change
the time horizon some of the views some
of the segmentations and the groupings
of the data again kind of real time
without having a person do that for uh a
business stakeholder and some of the
next steps is really evaluating the
tools that are out there for uh Genbi
like data bricks genie for example and
we're going to go into a much more
rigorous process of enriching our
catalog with metadata and documentation
and that's also going to come out of a
lot of the learnings that we got from uh
the research that we've done. So even if
we don't end up writing a GenBI agent
full-fledged end to end, we already got
a lot of value back from this and this
is really what allowed our senior
leadership team to continuously invest
in this project quarter over quarter.
One thing that I want to wrap up with is
just a couple of thoughts I had about
the future. So um I think we talk a lot
about how to prepare data. I think
that's going to be a huge area in the
market and they're going to be probably
a lot of companies and tools that are
going to help us with that. Uh building
very specific task specific models and
applications. I think a lot of startups
and companies are going to come up from
that area. Uh co-pilot is really making
sure that we meet the users where they
are. Uh and securing of models obviously
a very big thing. The last thing is the
one I the the one I want to focus on the
most because that's kind of a recent
thought that came to me a couple of
weeks ago. How we do pricing of SAS in
the Gen AI era. Uh this is really about
the fact that one individual person
today can be 10x more effective uh than
they used to be in the past. And then do
we price uh software based on seats or
do we price software based on how much
they used it or do we price software
based on the value that they got out of
it? Uh Salesforce is already
experimenting with that. So that the
data cloud product at Salesforce is
starting to be uh usage priced and not
seats priced. And I think this is going
to have a big impact on just the uh kind
of SAS economics worldwide.
uh and it it doesn't even matter if the
product itself is genai. It's really
about what does the person using the
product can do and what can they do in
their other time uh and whether it still
makes sense to price it by how many
employees you have or how much work you
get done with the employees that you
have.
That is me and thank you very much for
listening and thanks for not opening the
door on me.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat.